Inventory of the John Marshall Papers 1771-1959
Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
- Correspondence and Papers of John Marshall, Family Members and Other Individuals, 1771-1916, n.d. (Box 1-5)
  - Correspondence and Papers of John Marshall, 1771-1835, n.d., 269 items. (Box-folder 1-4)
    - Correspondence and Papers of John Marshall, 1800-1809., 28 items. (Box-folder 2:1-3)
      - J[ohn] Marshall, Richmond, [Virginia], to [?], [Jefferson County, Kentucky], 31 March 1801., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:2)
        Being sued by Virginia on a bond of security which he signed for Daniel Brodhead several years ago, Marshall has learned that the recipient of this letter was acquainted with the advertisements which Brodhead was required to post; he sends him a commission, therefore, and asks for his and Colonel Anderson's depositions concerning Brodhead and his business.
      - J[ohn] Marshall, Richmond, [Virginia], to Charles Cotesworth Pinckney, South Carolina, 21 November 1802., 3 pages. Pst of ALS. (Box-folder 2:2)
        Is composing a history of General Washington's life and requests information about the war in the Southern states, because General [?] Lincoln's letters to Washington in his [John Marshall's] possession do not tell much about the combined Franco-American operations at Savannah in 1779; send any important particulars respecting the siege of Charleston; is disgusted with the political world and hopes to see him [Charles Cotesworth Pinckney] in Richmond soon; asks about the political climate of South Carolina and thinks federalism may prevail in three districts in Virginia's state elections.
      - J[ohn] Marshall, Rawleigh [sic] [Raleigh, North Carolina], to "Polly" [Mary Willis (Ambler) Marshall], Richmond, Virginia, 2 January 1803., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:2)
        Discusses the mild but rainy weather and mentions various calamities which have befallen him: "15 silver dollars" of his "had worn through" his pocket "and sought their liberty in the sands of Carolina;" and when his man Peter unpacked his clothes, he discovered that he had not packed any of Marshall's breeches; "I thought I shou'd be sans culotte only one day," but all the town's were too busy to work for him; "I have the extreme mortification to pass the whole term without that important article of dress..."
        Including Pst of ALS. 3 pages.
      - 4 November 1804. J[ohn] Marshall, Richmond, [Virginia], to John M. Mason, [n.p.], 1 page. TCy of ALS. (Box-folder 2:2)
        Thanks him for an oration which he sent on the death of Alexander Hamilton; hopes that Hamilton's death will cast some odium upon dueling; was not aware that he had played a part in producing the commercial meet in Baltimore; did not know he resigned the emoluments of his military service.
        Printed in Dann, Mason Memoirs.
      - John Eager Howard, Baltimore, [Maryland], to John Marshall, Richmond, [Virginia], 14 November 1804., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 2:2)
        Has received his [John Marshall's] November 2 letter requesting information for his [John Marshall's] history of General Washington's life, and will send his recollections of many transactions as soon as he can put them to paper; he [John Marshall] should also contact Colonel [Bushrod] Washington; will send the book Campaigns of 1780 and 1781, supposedly written with [?] Tarleton's assistance, which contains more official documents than any other work and correct plans of some of the actions, if it will be of any use.
      - J[ohn] Marshall, Richmond, [Virginia], to "Polly" [Mary Willis (Ambler) Marshall], Fauquier Court House, [Virginia], 27 September 1805., 1 page. Pst of ALS. (Box-folder 2:2)
        Arrived at her mother's yesterday, and found her not as well as he had hoped; her sisters are well; forgot to pay his brother Charles five dollars for his [John Marshall] son John's schooling; things are badly conducted at his [John Marshall's] plantation.
        John Marshall House, Virginia State Library, Richmond, Virginia.
      - J[ohn] Marshall, Washington, [D.C.], to James M. Marshall, near Front Royal, Frederick County, Virginia, 13 February 1806., 3 pages. Pst of ALS. (Box-folder 2:2)
        Discusses the problems of the Fairfax lands and the people of Winchester; will endeavor to raise a considerable part of the money required for payment.
      - J[ohn] Marshall, Happy Creek, [Virginia], to John Ambler, Williamsburg, Virginia, 5 April 1806., 3 pages. Pst of ALS. (Box-folder 2:2)
        Asks for the money which he [John Ambler] owes him for payment for land; needs it to make his [John Marshall's] payment to Mr. [?] Fairfax, which fact he [John Ambler] knew; his [John Marshall's] brother William will take the contract off his [John Ambler's] hands if desired.
        University of Virginia, Charlottesville, Virginia.
      - J[ohn] Adams, Quincy, [Massachusetts], to John Marshall, [Washington, D.C.?], 17 July 1806., 2 pages. Pst of ALS. (Box-folder 2:2)
        Takes no offense at his [John Marshall] printing of his [John Adams] letters to Gen[era]l Washington in his [John Marshall's] biography of Washington; in detailing the events of the last years of Washington's life, he [John Marshall] "will run the gauntlet between two influential factions, armed with scorpions...;" but such an investigation must be made; comments upon his [John Adams] appointing Gen[era]l Washington to head of the army.
      - J[ohn] Marshall, Richmond, [Virginia], to James M[arkham] Marshall, Happy Creek, near Front Royal, Frederick [County, Virginia], 2 May 1808., 2 pages. Pst of ALS. (Box-folder 2:3)
        Has received his [James Markham Marshall's] letter enclosing Col. Thurston's deed; did not hear about his [James Markham Marshall's] suit with Stevens; Fitzhugh's note is in [?] Williams' hand but has yet to get process executed on him as he stays at different places in Maryland and can't be easily found; discusses arrangements made for their nephew Tom, with their brother William.
      - J[ohn] Marshall, Richmond, [Virginia], to Charles Cotesworth Pinckney, n.p., 21 September 1808., 3 pages. Pst of ALS. (Box-folder 2:3)
        Discusses politics and report of Mr. [?] Chesnut that the Democratic Party in South Carolina would unquestionably support him [Charles Cotesworth Pinckney]; the late convention at New York confided that "unless this point can be gained...we [the Federalists] shall again miscarry;" no times have been more perilous than the present because of the internal changes wrought "by a party always hostile to our constitution" and because of even greater external threats; if the present foreign policy with France is continued, the United States "will soon become an empty name" and will no longer be independent; has spent his time on agricultural pursuits instead of professional duty, and scarcely ever reads a newspaper, but the nation's troubles are too serious for him to continue to do so; the Virginia Federalists may win three or four seats in the next Congress, but there is no hope for the presidential election.
        Original is located in the Pinckney Papers,
      - J[ohn] Marshall, Richmond, [Virginia], to "the cashier of the bank of the United States," Philadelphia, [Pennsylvania], 28 September 1808., 1 page. Pst of ALS. (Box-folder 2:3)
        Requests him to pay James Brown one thousand dollars when his [John Marshall's] quarterly salary accrues on October 1.
      - J[ohn] Marshall, Richmond, [Virginia], to Charles Cotesworth Pinckney, South Carolina, 19 October 1808., 3 pages. Pst of ALS. (Box-folder 2:3)
        Richmond Federalists have mutinied, and have recommended to their brethren throughout Virginia to support the Monroe ticket; was out of town but attempts to explain the reasons for such action.
      - [John Marshall, Richmond, Virginia, to John Eliot, n.p.], [20 September 1809]., 1 page. TCy of AL. (Box-folder 2:3)
        Is honored to be chosen as a corresponding member of the Massachusetts Historical Society; as he will not return to Washington, [D.C.] until February, perhaps some member of Congress might find room in his baggage for the volume he [John Eliot] mentioned.
        Massachusetts Historical Society, Boston, Massachusetts.
    - Correspondence and Papers of John Marshall, 1810-1819., 37 items. (Box-folder 2:3-6)
      - [John Marshall], n.p., to John Eliot, Richmond, [Virginia], 23 April 1810., 1 page. TCy of AL. (Box-folder 2:3)
        Asks him to send the collections of the Society.
      - Bushrod Washington, Mount Vernon, [Fairfax County, Virginia,] to Chief Justice [John] Marshall, Richmond, [Virginia], 2 May 1810., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:3)
        Discusses arrangements being made with Mr. [?] Willing and [?] Francis to take his [John Marshall] two sons, [John and James Keith Marshall], into their counting house when they reach the age of 16; outlines their recommended course of study before then; Mr. [?] Waln[?] will receive his [John Marshall] other son, [Edward Carrington Marshall], into his mercantile establishment, if the precarious state of the country: commerce permits it, when he comes of age; asks if he should send his [John Marshall] half-pipe of wine to Richmond by way of Norfolk.
        Including Ph. 1 page. Incomplete.
      - J[ohn] Marshall, Richmond, [Virginia] to Charles Lee, Alexandria, [Virginia], 7 May 1810., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:3)
        Acknowledges letters of Apr. 22, 29, and 30. Outlines patents to Virginia land. Philip Pendleton, Anderson, and Hunter involved in caveat; advises against use of treasury warrant for 1,180 acres. Colston. Decision in Hunter and Fairfax case, decided in favor of Hunter. Asks Lee's opinion as to appeal to Supreme Court; John Marshall favors appeal; sending record; Jones to be engaged as attorney to help Lee. Cause precedent for pending caveats if Supreme Court "against us," save expense; if "in our favor," probably respected or ascertain points for ultimate determination "in our favor."
      - Timothy] Pickering, Senate Chamber, [Washington, D.C.] to John Marshall, Richmond, Virginia, 25 February 1811., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:3)
        Is gratified by the compliments he [John Marshall] paid to him in his last letter, and hopes to continue his service to the country; has not learned if [?] Serruier is charged with any special orders to the government; [?] Turreau has for some time desired to return to France; asks him [John Marshall] for a proper statement of an anecdote concerning Temple Franklin and Benjamin Franklin Bache's unsuccessful attempts to establish a newspaper, which he [John Marshall] related to him last year.
      - J[ohn] Marshall, Richmond, [Virginia], to James Monroe, n.p., 25 June 1812., 1 page. TCy of ALS. (Box-folder 2:4)
        Upon his return from the "laborious relaxation" of his farm, he found the President's [Madison] message, the report of the committee of foreign relations, and the declaration of war against Great Britain.
      - J[ames] Madison, [Washington, D.C.], to John Marshall, [Washington, D.C.], 12 October [1812?]., 1 page. AL. (Box-folder 2:4)
        Accepts his invitation to dine with him.
      - [James] Monroe, [Washington, D.C.], to John Marshall, [Washington, D.C.], [12 October 1812?]., 1 page. AL. (Box-folder 2:4)
        Accepts his invitation to dine with him on Wednesday.
      - J[ohn] Marshall, Richmond, [Virginia], to Lyttleton [Littleon] Wailer Tazewell, Norfolk, [Virginia], 18 January 1813., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:4)
        Cannot direct the special court he [Littleon Wailer Tazewell] requested because the law authorizing a circuit judge to perform the duties of a district judge is limited only to the case of the disability of an existing district judge, and does not extend to the case of a vacancy of that office; has notified the Secretary of State of the public hardships if an appointment is postponed.
      - J[ohn] Marshall, Richmond, [Virginia] to [John B. Colvin, n.p.], 7 May 1813., 2 pages. TCy of ALS. (Box-folder 2:4)
        Received a copy of his book, Historical Letters, and asks Mr. [?] Pleasant to sign him up as a subscriber; comments favorably upon the work, a comparative history of the nations of the world.
      - J[ohn] Marshall, Richmond, [Virginia], to Bushrod Washington, Mount Vernon, [Fairfax County, Virginia], 25 May 1813., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:4)
        Received his cheek for $500 and letter upon his [John Marshall] return from North Carolina; will receive four sets of The Life of Washington from Mr. [Mason Locke] Weems; discusses a case of Admiralty business which he had just heard in circuit court and asks for his [Bushrod Washington] opinion; is anxious to terminate next court's business so he can devote himself to the farm.
      - J[ohn] Marshall, Richmond, [Virginia], to Judge [Bushrod] Washington, Philadelphia, [Pennsylvania], 19 April 1814., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:4)
        Discusses whether the power to pass bankruptcy laws resides in the states or in the federal government; discusses part of Constitution which inhibits passage of "law impairing the obligation of contracts" and how it relates to bankruptcy laws; says he [Bushrod Washington] heard the argument and his opinion could be relied upon better than his.
      - Frederick County [Virginia] Court release proved to John Marshall and James M. Marshall sworn to by Charles Magill, Henry Daingerfield, Thomas McKewan, and Leroy Daingerfield, 2 August 1814., 2 pages. Pst of AD. (Box-folder 2:4)
      - J[ohn] Marshall, Richmond, [Virginia] to Bushrod Washington, "Mount Vernon," [Virginia], 29 December [1814]., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:4)
        Asks what provision is made for them at their session; will he make accommodations for them; asks "Are we to have peace; or is the war to be continued till we are dismembered?"
      - Notice written by Marshall while in Washington D.C. advertising for the return of a strayed or stolen bay saddle horse and offering a liberal reward for it, 10 March 1815., 1 page. Pst of ADS. (Box-folder 2:4)
      - J[ohn] Marshall, Richmond, [Virginia], to Bushrod Washington, "Mount Vernon," [Virginia], 16 March 1815., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:4)
        Asks him [Bushrod Washington] to ask the counting house of Messrs. Willing & Francis if they are still willing to take his [John Marshall] fifteen year old son James (now a student at Cambridge) into their firm.
      - J[ohn] Marshall, n.p., to Bushrod Washington, Philadelphia, [Pennsylvania], [April 1815]., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:4)
        Has made inquiries in response to his letter; land for which taxes are unpaid before August will be sold; payment can be made to the Sheriff of the county; discusses George Washington letters and how he thinks they should be published; asks him to settle a newspaper account for him.
      - J[ohn] Marshall, Happy Creek, [Virginia], to John Ambler, Richmond, Virginia, 23 October 1815., 3 pages. Pst of ALS. (Box-folder 2:4)
        Encloses a copy of a letter from Robert Colston in which he [Robert Colston] complains of his [John Ambler's] withholding payment and threatens him John Ambler] with a lawsuit; suggests that he [John Ambler] give Mr. Colston an order on Mr. [?] Smith for the amount in question with as little delay as possible.
      - J[ohn] Marshall, Richmond, [Virginia], to Bushrod Washington, "Mount Vernon," [Virginia], 10 September 1816. (Box-folder 2:4)
        Discusses civil admiralty jurisdiction about which he had formed an opinion from the characters in a case of piracy not from precedent; wishes him to discuss revision of "The Life" [of George Washington] with Mr. Wayne while he is in Philadelphia; explains his ideas for the organization of the work; says it must be prepared at leisure and not offered until there is a demand for it.
      - J[ohn] Marshall, Richmond, [Virginia], to "My dear Nephew," [Martin Marshall ?, Winchester, Virginia ?]. 10 September 1816., 1 page. Pst of ALS (original, Breckenridge-Marshall Papers). (Box-folder 2:4)
        Encloses a memorandum from the Auditors' office concerning William Marshall's lands in Nason and Franklin counties, [Kentucky], and a letter which he wishes delivered to his sister [Jane (Marshall) Taylor]; she desired him to engage a house for her at Fauquier Court House.
        Encloses a memorandum from the Filson club. 2 pages. Including TCy of ALS.
      - J[ohn] Marshall, Richmond, [Virginia], to [Governeur Morris], n.p., 3 October 1816., 2 pages. Df[?] of ALS. (Box-folder 2:4)
        After reading the recipient's address to the New York Historical Society, he sends him his thoughts on the study of history.
      - J[ohn] Marshall, Washington, [D.C.], to "Polly" [Mary Willis (Ambler) Marshall], Richmond, Virginia, 14 February 1817., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:5)
        Discusses the Washington social life; is impressed with the French minister and his wife [?]; [William] Wirt arrived yesterday but he brought no letters; warns her to take enough blankets to arm herself against the intense cold when she goes to Chiccahoniiny [sic] on February 21.
        Including Pat of ALS. 2 pages.
      - Ja[me]s Monroe, Washington [D.C.], to John Marshall, [Washington D.C.], 1 March 1817., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 2:5)
        Asks Marshall to administer the Presidential oath to him.
        Including Pst of ALS. 1 page. Also including TCy of ALS. 1 page.
      - J[ohn] Marshall, Washington, [D.C.], to [James Monroe, Washington, D.C.], 1 March 1817., 1 page. Ph of ALS. (Box-folder 2:5)
        Agrees to administer the Presidential oath of office to James Monroe.
        Including Ph. neg. of ALS. 1 page.
      - J[ohn] Marshall, Washington, [D.C.], to "Polly" [Mary Willis (Ambler) Marshall, Richmond, Virginia], 16 February 1818., 1 page. (Box-folder 2:5)
        Has read in Jaquelin [Marshall]'s last letter news of her ill health, and advises her not to expose herself to the cold in her fears of being too warm; he is in good health and is busily employed. 1 page. ALS. Including ALS on verso from John Marshall, to his son [John?], discussing farm matters, and asking him to receive the overseer's letter concerning such things as preparing the soil with plaster of paris grubbing, cutting, and burning; does not want him to send packages by post, but by private conveyance if available; sends him a note for $60 to pay Mr.[?] Cocke for 20 barrels of corn; asks about James [Keith Marshall] and hopes he has engaged in a course of reading.
        Also Including TCy of ALS. l page. Also Including Pst of ALS. 2 pages.
      - Mark L. DesCaves, Baltimore, [Maryland], to John Marshall, Richmond, Virginia, [ante 31 March 1818]., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 2:5)
        Encloses a letter from General [Marie Joseph Paul Yves Roch Gilbert du Motier, Marquis de] Lafayette, which he has been unable to deliver in person, as the General had instructed; saw Juge [sic] [Bushrod] Washington several months earlier, and was informed by him that Mr. [?] Graham returned to Lafayette the General's papers, which Marshall had borrowed.
        Including ALS, 22 April 1817, from [Marquis de] Lafayette, La grange, [France], to John Marshall, United States, Virginia. Introducing his friend M. des Caves; praises Marshall's biography of Washington and says that most of his correspondence with Washington was lost during the French Revolution; mentions the copies of Washington's letters to him, which he desires to be returned to him by Bushrod Washington; recommends M. desCaves to him [John Marshall].
      - William] Wirt, [Washington, D.C.], to [John] Marshall, [Washington, D.C.], [March 1818?]., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 2:5)
        Is unable to accept his invitation to dine with him because of his health.
      - Willia]m Wirt, [Washington, D.C.], to John Marshall, [Washington, D.C.], [March 1818?]., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 2:5)
        Requests that his case before the [Supreme] Court be given a day's respite as the extremes of weather have incapacitated him.
      - Correspondence and Papers, 1819., 10 items. (Box-folder 2:5)
        - J[ohn] Marshall, Washington, [D.C.], to Gulian C. Verplanck, [New York?], 27 February 1819., 1 page. Pst of ALS (Box-folder 2:5)
          Has received and finally read the address which he presented to the New York Historical Society; was much pleased with its clarity and lucid arrangement, and feels the public would like to see more from his pen.
        - J[ohn] Marshall, Richmond, [Virginia], to Joseph Story, [Salem, Massachusetts], 24 March 1819., 2 pages. TCy of ALS. (Box-folder 2:5)
          Asks for information about nail making machines in Boston, for a friend of his who might like to purchase one; the opinion in the Banks case "has roused the sleeping spirit of Virginia" and will be attacked in the papers.
        - J[ohn] Marshall, Richmond, [Virginia], to Bushrod Washington, Philadelphia, [Pennsylvania], 27 March [1819]., 3 pages. ALS. Signature mutilated. (Box-folder 2:5)
          Asks him to purchase books for his [John Marshall] nephew, [?] Taylor who is at school in Kentucky; makes arrangements to pay the bookseller and [?] Deiplaine, and to have him send the volumes, including " Terence [sic] & Livy in Latin, Longinus, Thucydides, & Demosthenes in Greek, also Xenophens retreat of the 10,000" to his [John Marshall] brother, Doctor [Louis] Marshall, in Kentucky; discusses dissatisfaction of Virginian politicians with the Supreme Court's opinion on the Bank question; "we shall be denounced bitterly in the papers... and we shall undoubtedly be condemned as a pack of consolidating aristocratics;" mentions unexpected and long unheard of financial distress of Richmond merchants.
          Including TCy of ALS. 1 page. Also including Pst of ALS. 2 pages.
        - [John Marshall, Richmond, Virginia], to Jaquelin B. Harvie, n.p., [March - April 1819]., 3 pages. AL. (Box-folder 2:5)
          Extracted from a letter of Joseph Story's to John Marshall describing a $1000 nail-making machine invented by Mr. [?] Perkins, and used extensively in the Amesbury Factory near Salem, Massachusetts; also describes two different, less expensive models patented by Mr. [?] Reed [?], and discusses arrangements for their sale and delivery.
        - J[ohn] M[arshall], Richmond, [Virginia,] to Bushrod Washington, Alexandria, [Virginia], 28 April 1819., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 2:5)
          Discusses an error in his published manuscript [of a court decision?] which he [John Marshall] wishes Mr. [ ] Bronson to correct.
          Including TCy of ALS. 1 page. Including Pst of ALS. 1 page.
        - J[ohn] Marshall, Richmond, [Virginia], to Joseph Story, [Salem, Massachusetts], 27 May 1819., 3 pages. TCy of ALS. (Box-folder 2:6)
          Discusses the gross misrepresentations the Democratic-Republicans have attributed to the Court's opinion in the Bank case in order to excite ferment in the masses; asks his advice on a case in Admiralty Court, that the Little Charles, libeled for violating the 1808 Embargo Act.
        - [John Marshall, Richmond, Virginia, to Bushrod Washington, Mount Vernon, Fairfax County, Virginia], [28 June 1819]., 1 page. TCy of AL. (Box-folder 2:6)
          If the publication of his [John Marshall] work has not yet commenced, he would rather have the signature changed to "A Constitutionalist"; the letters of Amphyction and of Hampden have had more influence in the country than in Richmond; hopes some respectable legislators will refute them.
        - J[ohn] Marshall, Richmond, [Virginia], to Joseph Story, Salem, Massachusetts, 13 July 1819., 3 pages. TCy of ALS. (Box-folder 2:6)